Fred W. Householder papers, 1945-1994 C450
Indiana University Archives
Fred W. Householder papers
1945-1994
1950-1989
Indiana University Archives
Householder, Fred W. (Fred Walter), 1913-1994
C450
13.6 cubic feet 14 boxes
Fred Walter Householder Jr. was a prominent professor of linguistics and classics at Indiana University Bloomington and an important figure within the field of linguistics. The collection contains materials from courses Householder taught at Indiana University, research files of his studies abroad, language materials and records from the Linguistic Atlas Project, or the LANCS project.
Access Restrictions
Select files closed to researchers due to student papers with grades. Advance notice required for access to collection.
Biographical Note
Born on February 1, 1913 in Wichita Falls, Texas, Fred Walter Householder began his study of languages at an early age by reading the dictionary. After completing high school in Burlington, Vermont he attended the University of Vermont, where he received his A.B. in Greek in 1932. The following year he entered graduate school at Columbia University where he took his first linguistics course from scholar Louis Gray. Completing his M.A. in 1934, he continued his studies in pursuit of his Ph.D., receiving the Drisler (1935-1936) and the Seymour Fellowships (1936-1937) which allowed him to study at the American School of Classical Studies in Athens, Greece. While in Greece, Householder took up studying ancient doors and sills on top of his studies of the Greek language. While working towards his Ph.D. he married Clarice Bagley on February 6, 1935.
Following the completion of his Ph.D. in 1941, Householder continued to lecture at Columbia University in Greek and Latin until 1946, at which point he took a position as an associate professor of classics at Allegheny College. Two years later, he joined the Indiana University faculty as an assistant professor of classics where he quickly rose through the ranks being named associate professor in 1951 and full professor in 1956. Over the next several years Householder served a variety of outside roles: a visiting professor at Cornell University, the University of Michigan, the University of Hawaii and as a Guggenheim Fellow (1958-1959). He retired from IU in 1983.
During his time at Indiana University, Householder played an instrumental part in the elevation of the university's linguistics program to departmental status. Initially, there was just an interdisciplinary linguistics committee which formed the nucleus for the later establishment of a linguistic department. From 1959-1962 he served as the chairman of the Linguistic Committee. In 1963 the College of Arts and Sciences officially created the Department of Linguistics of which he served as the chair from 1974 through 1980.
Although Householder held a busy schedule he always continued to research and write on a variety of areas including: Greek, Latin, Azerbaijani and much more. He and his colleague even installed the first Sona-Graph machine in the department's phonics laboratory. He was an active member in multiple professional societies and associations including: American Philological Association, Linguistic Society of America, Archaeological Institute of American, Modern Greek Studies Association and the American Association of Phonetic Science (participating on boards and committees too). He also wrote and participated in multiple research grants including for the United States Air Force on Turkic, specifically Azerbaijani; American Council of Learned Societies on an English textbook for Greeks; Contract with Rome Air Development Command on Information Retrieval; a National Science Foundation (NSF) and the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) grants.
Fred Walter Householder Jr. died on January 4, 1994. He was survived by his wife Clarice (Bagley) Householder and their two daughters Alison Prindle and Lynn Householder.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series. The first series, Research (1946-1994), is further organized into six sub-series: ATLAS Project, Language files, Research Index Cards, Spectrograph research, and General files. The other series included are: Publications, reviews and writings (1940-1993), Teaching files (1954-1969), Correspondence (1945-1989) and Subject files (1946-1994).
The Subject files (1946-1994), Teaching files (1954-1969) and Correspondence (1945-1989) series are all arranged in alphabetical order by folder heading. The Publications, reviews and writing Series (1940-1993) is further organized into two Sub-series: Publications and writings, and Reviews, both are in chronological order.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is organized into five series: Research (1946-1994), Publications, reviews and writings (1940-1993), Teaching files (1954-1969), Correspondence (1945-1989) and Subject files (1946-1994).
The Research series is further organized into six sub-series: ATLAS Project (1952-1976), Language files (1958-1962), Research index cards (undated), Spectrograph research (1952-1971), and Subject files (1960-1971).
The ATLAS Project sub-series consists of research notebooks used to collect information about various participants day-to-day use of language. The ATLAS project is a large collection of linguistic studies performed for the last 80 years around the United States by various scholars. Researchers of varying disciplinary backgrounds including Householder interviewed informants, listening for specific target information such as varying regional dialects and use of words. Householder specifically researched the geographic locations of Indiana, Kentucky and Illinois specifically known as LANCS. The ATLAS Project Sub-series remains in Householder's original order.
The Language files include materials such as newspapers in Azerbaijani, research notebooks, language worksheets including grammar and phonetics, dictionary descriptions and language transcripts. Languages include but are not limited to: Azerbaijani, Greek, Latin, and Quechua. Files are in alphabetical order.
The Research index cards sub-series totals eight small boxes of index cards pertaining to the Latin and Greek people, places, grammar and other miscellaneous topics. Two additional small boxes of index cards include an index of books alphabetized by author and place and miscellaneous information on the Greek Island of Delos. The boxes maintain Householder's original order as best as possible.
The Spectrograph research sub-series contains sound spectrograms (graphic representations of speech patterns and vocal influxes) and research materials related to the spectrographs. Files are in alphabetical order by folder heading.
The last Research sub-series is Subject files, which includes research on linguistics, Householder's Seymour Fellowship research on ancient doors and sills, concordances, and miscellaneous documents. Files are in alphabetical order by folder heading.
The Publications, reviews and writings series (1940-1993) is further organized into two sub-series: Publications and writings (1940-1993) and Reviews (1954-1987). Publications and writings include both published and unpublished materials written by Householder, including: "Variation in Early Greek," 1973, "Inference or Presupposition," 1977 and Spoken Azerbaijani I by Householder and Mansour Lotfi (published in 1965 under Basic Course in Azerbaijani). The Reviews sub-series contains articles reviewed by Householder.
The Teaching files (1954-1969) series is compiled of student work, exams, and teaching materials used for classes. A large portion of this series is restricted due to student grade information.
The Correspondence (1945-1989) series includes letters from Greece, Bobbs-Merrill Company (Indianapolis Book Publisher,) the Linguistic Society of America, Cambridge University Press, and correspondence between Householder and sociolinguist, anthropologist and folklorist Dell Hathaway Hymes.
The final series of Subject files (1946-1994) contains biographical materials, and materials relating to Householder affiliations and committee participation both inside and outside of the University.
Related Material
Additional publications and research materials may be accessed in IUScholarworks.
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database.
Acquisition Information
Accession numbers: 2011/073
Appraisal
The majority of Dr. Householder's collection has remained intact at the archives. Duplicate materials including articles, course hand-outs and other miscellaneous paper work were discarded.
Linguistics teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Householder, Fred W. (Fred Walter), 1913-1994 -- Archives; Householder, Fred W. (Fred Walter), 1913-1994 -- Correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Linguistics -- Faculty -- Archives
- Research files, 1946-1994 (Box 1)
  - ATLAS Project, 1952-1976 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1976 (Box 1)
    - Linguistic Atlas of the U.S.A. and Canada Short worksheets, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Short Atlas Worksheets, undated (Box 1)
    - Questionnaire, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
    - Research Notebooks, all, undated (Box 1)
      - NC 100.11 MO 19 ILL KAN KAN S (Box 1)
      - NC 108 2 MO 16 ILL EDG PA F (Box 1)
      - NC 115.3 b-6 ILL EDW AL J (Box 1)
      - NC 131.1 B19 IND POR VA W (Box 1)
      - NC 131.2 RIM IND POR VLP G (Box 1)
      - NC 132.1 MO 9 IND ELK GO W (Box 1)
      - NC 132.2 MO 5 IND ELK GO M (Box 1)
      - NC 133.2 T-20 IND MAR PI H (Box 1)
      - NC 134.1 MO 13 IND ALL BE P (Box 1)
      - NC 134.2 MO-2 IND ALL BE L (Box 1)
      - NC 135.2 B 15 IND WAB UR K (Box 1)
      - NC 136.1 LT 1 IND CAR DE J (Box 1)
      - NC 136.2 B21 IND CAR DE H (Box 1)
      - NC 136.21 B-22 IND CAR DE D (Box 1)
      - NC 137.3 B-20 IND WAR WI H (Box 1)
      - NC 138.1 HO-3 IND ADA DE T (Box 1)
      - NC 138.1 MO 18 IND MO B (Box 1)
      - NC 138.2 B18 IND AD BE B (Box 1)
      - NC 138.2 B17 IND AD BE R (Box 1)
      - NC 139.1 T11 IND BOO LE D (Box 1)
      - NC 139.2 MO 7 IND BOO JA H (Box 1)
      - NC 140.1 MO 1 IND MAD PE H (Box 1)
      - NC 140.2 T-19 IND MAD AND W-J (Box 1)
      - NC 141.2 B16 IND RAN WR T (Box 1)
      - NC 142.1 MO 10 IND PARK RO S (Box 1)
      - NC 142.2 MO 14 IND PARK RO P (Box 1)
      - NC 143.1 T 12 IND MAR BD H (Box 1)
      - NC 143.2 MO 15 IND MAR CU W (Box 1)
      - NC 143.3 MO 8 IND MAR IN D (Box 1)
      - NC 144.1 B-12 IND RUSH MI 1 (Box 1)
      - NC 144.2 B-11 IND RUSH MI P (Box 1)
      - NC 145.1 MO 4 IND CLAY BG E (Box 1)
      - NC 145.2 MO 11 IND CLAY BG C (Box 1)
      - NC 146.1 B-14 IND FRA BR S (Box 1)
      - NC 146.2 B-13 IND FRA BR R (Box 1)
      - NC 148.2 MO 3 IND BRO NA C (Box 1)
      - NC 149.2 B-19 IND RIP VE T (Box 1)
      - NC 150.1 MO 6 IND KNOX WH S (Box 1)
      - NC 150.2 B-8 IND KNOX WH M (Box 1)
      - NC 151.1 B-23 IND ORA ORL R (Box 1)
      - NC 151.1 OR 1 IND ORA OR M (Box 1)
      - NC 151.3 MO 12 IND ORA ORL G (Box 1)
      - NC 152(6).1 B-1 IND HAR CO B (Box 1)
      - NC 152.2 B-10 IND CLA CH M (Box 1)
      - NC 153.2 B-4 IND G1B PA P (Box 1)
      - NC 154.1 B-2 IND VAN EVR (Box 2)
      - NC 154.2 ROM IND V DB EV L (Box 2)
      - NC 155.1 B-3 IND SPE RO S (Box 2)
      - NC 155.2 B-7 IND SPE RO P (Box 2)
      - NC 156.3 B-5 IND HAR CO LH (Box 2)
      - NC 162.1 T-18 KY LIV SM C-P (Box 2)
      - NC 162.2 T-17 KY LIV SM CH (Box 2)
      - NC 163.1 T-4 KY WEB DI C (Box 2)
      - NC 163.2 T KY WEB SE D (Box 2)
      - NC 164 B.1 T-21 KY HAR CO S (Box 2)
      - NC 164.2 HO-2 KY HAN HAW R (Box 2)
      - NC 164.21 HO 6 KY HAN HA K (Box 2)
      - NC 165.1 T-3 KY BUL SH H (Box 2)
      - NC 165.2 H 1 KY BUL WP A (Box 2)
      - NC 173.21 T KY TRI CAL F (Box 2)
      - NC 174.1 T-5 KY MU GR F (Box 2)
      - NC 174.2 T-6 KY MUH GR B (Box 2)
      - NC 175.1 T-8 KY LOG AU S (Box 2)
      - NC 175.2 T-7 KY LOG LE M (Box 2)
      - NC 176.1 HO 5 KY NEL BA A (Box 2)
      - NC 176.2 HO 4 KY NEL BA C (Box 2)
      - NC 180.1 T-9 KY GRE GR L (Box 2)
  - Language files, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
    - Azerbaijani (Box 2)
      - Blue books, undated (Box 2)
      - Files, undated (Box 2)
      - In print, undated; (3 folders) (Box 2)
      - Junctive, undated (Box 2)
      - Newspapers, undated (Box 2)
      - Notebooks, phonology notes, I and II, undated (Box 2)
      - Notebooks, III, IV, V, undated (Box 2)
      - Text Files, undated (Box 2)
    - Bongo-Bongo, undated (Box 2)
    - British non-subjunctives, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Columbia language notes, undated (Box 2)
    - English (Box 2)
      - Aspect Tenses, undated (Box 2)
      - Canonic Shapes, undated (Box 2)
      - Syntax, undated (Box 2)
    - Greek (Box 2)
      - Ancient, ext., undated (Box 2)
        Conditions Governing Access
        (Restricted)
      - Beginning Greek: Oral, 1962 (Box 2)
      - Bible Soc. Semantic Project for Greek, undated (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1951-1967; undated; (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Modern, undated (Box 2)
      - Modern Project, undated (Box 3)
      - Oral Greek, Latin cases, undated (Box 3)
      - Perfect, undated (Box 3)
      - Verb maze, undated (Box 3)
      - Vowels, undated (Box 3)
    - Italic and Proto-Latin, undated (Box 3)
    - Kiowa Person [spelling], undated (Box 3)
    - Latin (Box 3)
      - Phonology, undated (Box 3)
      - Rules for a Segment of English Syntax, miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
      - Structure, summer 1958 (Box 3)
      - Latin stuff, undated (Box 3)
    - Pame, undated (Box 3)
    - Quechua (Box 3)
      - Chuquimia Reel 5, 1959 (Box 3)
      - Dictionary-Preliminary Description by: Pete Kurtz, undated (Box 3)
      - Ramp, undated (Box 3)
      - Reel 4 Ch. Transcription RWB, September 1962 (Box 3)
      - Reel 5, undated (Box 3)
      - Tape 2, undated (Box 3)
    - Sanskrit, undated (Box 3)
    - Shawnee (Box 3)
      - General, undated; (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Episodes, Transcriptions, undated (Box 3)
      - Text by Voeglin, C.F., undated (Box 3)
    - Syntax problems and solutions, undated (Box 3)
    - Upper Chehalis, undated (Box 3)
  - Research index cards, undated (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    [The majority of the cards appear to be in Latin and Greek]
    - Miscellaneous Index Cards, undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous: Greek Island of Delos and Unrestored, undated (Box 3.1)
    - Indices: A-Z: Index of books alphabetized by Author, Places, A-I-O: Buildings, A-T: Gods, Festivals, Epithets, Religions etc., and Reverse, undated (Box 3.2)
    - Greek: Xen, Herodotus, Plato, Isocrates, Orators besides Dem. and Isoc., Miscellaneous, Greek grammar etc, undated (Box 4.1)
    - Miscellaneous Latin: Preps, in, In (Acc.), People, Places, Things, Abst., Time, IN CABL, undated (Box 4.2)
    - Latin grammar and tenses, undated (Box 4.3)
    - Miscellaneous Latin, undated (Box 4.4)
    - Miscellaneous and Latin, undated (Box 5.1)
    - Latin grammar, undated (Box 5.2)
    - Latin grammar, undated (Box 5.3)
    - Miscellaneous Latin, undated (Box 5.4)
  - Spectrograph research, (1952-1971) (Box 6)
    - A Characterization of Themne Vowels, undated (Box 6)
    - Acoustic Phonetics (Finnish,), undated (Box 6)
    - Albanian, Hungarian and Maori, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Apache and Papago, undated (Box 6)
    - Aushu's tape, undated (Box 6)
    - Austin's Phonology tapes, undated (Box 6)
    - Azerbaijan, undated; (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Azi, undated (Box 6)
    - Bulgarian, undated (Box 6)
    - Chao's 1952 Spectrograms (Box 6)
    - Demonstration Spectrograms, undated (Box 6)
    - Efik - Double Nasals, Spring 1968 (Box 6)
    - English, some Danish, Italian, Spanish (Jones review,), undated (Box 6)
    - English (Box 6)
      - Comparison of 4 Speakers of Louisville Kentucky Origin, undated (Redacted for Privacy) (Box 6)
      - Pat Huffman and others, undated (Box 6)
    - Extra copies, miscellaneous, undated (Box 6)
    - Finnish (Box 6)
      - Pronunciation, undated (Box 6)
      - 1959 (Redacted for Privacy) (Box 6)
    - Glottal Stops etc., undated (Box 6)
    - Greek, undated (Box 6)
    - Modern Greek Tapes, undated (Box 6)
    - Haitian Creole, undated (Box 6)
    - Hauasupai, undated (Box 6)
    - Italian (Bucca mostly,), undated (Box 6)
    - Jakobson, Robnan (Festschrift,), undated (Box 6)
    - Kaiwa (Bridgeman,), undated (Box 6)
      (Redacted for Privacy)
    - Kerinchi, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Korean Double Consonants, undated (Box 6)
    - Miriam Australian and Talanty (Australia,), undated (Box 6)
    - Nʸanumata Phonology, January 1962 (Box 6)
    - Norwegian and Polish Vowel Charts, undated (Box 6)
    - Phonetics (Box 6)
      - Class, 1957-1958 (Box 6)
      - Class (Old), undated (Box 6)
      - Laboratory, 1967 (Box 6)
      - Spectra, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Russian Vowels, undated (Box 6)
    - Sibilants and Fricatives, undated (Box 6)
      (SEE ALSO: Whisper)
    - Some Aspects of Intonation, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Sona-Graph Instructions, undated (Box 6)
    - Spectrograms and Report on Acoustic Phonetics, undated (Box 6)
    - Spectrograms, miscellaneous, undated (Box 6)
    - Stops, undated (Box 6)
    - TAMIL (Box 6)
    - Tests & noises, undated (Box 6)
    - Thai Phonetic Study, undated (Box 6)
    - Tones in Twi, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Twi and Eskimo, undated (Box 6)
    - U.K. Low German, undated (Box 6)
    - Upper Chehalis, undated (Box 6)
    - Upper Chehalis and Salish, undated (Box 6)
    - Urdu, undated (Box 6)
    - Various Settings-New Spectrograph, undated (Box 6)
    - Vietnamese, undated (Box 6)
    - Visiograms, 1968-1969 (Box 6)
    - Vowels, undated; (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Whisper & h,m, undated (Box 6)
  - General files, (1960-1971) (Box 7)
    - Absolute Breakers, 1960-1962 (Box 7)
    - B Modals, undated (Box 7)
    - CPS and semitones, undated (Box 7)
    - Concordances, undated; (Box 13) (Box 7)
    - Grant Report, 1965 (Box 7)
    - Latin Grammer, Quod and Quia in Geoffrey of Monmouth, undated (Box 7)
    - Linguistic Research Project (Box 7)
      - Adjectives before that-clauses in English, 1964 (Box 7)
      - Indiana University, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous Articles, undated; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Notebook - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 7)
    - "Phonology in Generative Grammar", 1962 (Box 7)
    - Quarterly Reports (Box 7)
      - 3, 4, and 5, 1960-1961 (Box 7)
      - 6 and 7, 1961-1962 (Box 7)
    - Quid vs. Quac research, 1960 (Box 7)
    - Semantic/Lexical Change, undated (Box 7)
    - Seybold-Thoreau comments, 1971 (Box 7)
    - Seymour Fellowship (Box 7)
      - Door and Sills (Box 7)
        - General, undated (Box 7)
        - Delos, undated (Box 7)
        - Epidaurus, undated (Box 7)
        - Macedonia, Thasos, Philippi, Olythus, undated (Box 7)
        - Roman bath, Byzantine House, etc., undated (Box 7)
      - Tabular Summary of Spoken word count by: Joe E. Pierce, undated (Box 7)
    - Sketches and Drawings - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 7)
    - Topicaliz. XII, Passive, Ergative, etc. [Spelling], undated (Box 7)
- Publications, reviews, and writings, 1940-1993 (Box 7)
  - Publications and writings, 1940-1993 (Box 7)
    - "The Mock Decrees in Lucian", 1940 (Box 7)
    - "IIAPΩIΔIA", 1941 (Box 7)
    - "A Ptolemaic Graffito in New York," with D.W. Prakken, 1945 (Box 7)
    - "A Descriptive Analysis of Latin Declension", 1947 (Box 7)
    - "Nominative for Accusative", 1949 (Box 7)
    - "Accent, Juncture, Intonation, and My Grandfather's Reader", 1957 (Box 7)
    - "Pa-ro and Mycenaean Cases", 1959 (Box 7)
    - "First Thoughts on Syntactic Indices", 1960 (Box 7)
    - Opening Statement from "The Viewpoint of Linguistics," Style in Language, 1960 (Box 7)
    - "Early Greek -j-," Mycenean, 1961; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "On Linguistic Terms", 1961; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "Azerbaijani Onomatopes", 1961-1962 (Box 7)
    - "The Distributional Determination of English Phonemes", 1962 (Box 7)
    - "Lists in Grammars, in Logic Methodology and Philosophy of Science", 1962 (Box 7)
    - "On the Uniqueness of Semantic Mapping", 1962; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "Greek Diglossia", 1963 (Box 7)
    - "A Morphophonemic Question and a Spelling Rule", 1964 (Box 8)
    - "Three Dreams of Modern Greek Phonology", 1964; (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - "On some Recent Claims in Phonological Theory", 1965 (Box 8)
    - "Phonological Theory: A brief comment", 1965 (Box 8)
    - Spoken Azerbaijani I by Fred W. Householder and Mansour Lotfi (Published in 1965 under Basic Course in Azerbaijani), (12 folders) (Box 8)
    - "Distinctive Features and Phonetic Features," Jakobson Festschrift, ca., 1966 (Box 8)
    - "Word Classes: Ancient Greek" (draft), 1967 (Box 8)
    - Current Trends in Linguistics by Fred Householder and Gregory Naggy, 1968-1972 (Box 8)
    - "The Principal step in Linguistic Change", 1972 (Box 8)
    - "A Problem in Rule Ordering?", 1972 (Box 8)
    - "Vowel Overlap in Azerbaijani", 1972 (Box 8)
    - "On Arguments from asterisks", 1972-1973 (Box 8)
    - "Variation in Early Greek", 1973; (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - "Comment on Satyanarayana's "A Proposal Concerning The Revision of the Phase- Structure Component", 1974 (Box 8)
    - "Apollonius Dysolus and the Origins of Deep Structure", 1977 (Box 8)
    - "Inference or Presupposition?", 1977 (Box 8)
    - "Innateness and Improvisability", 1977 (Box 8)
    - "Old Bottles, or The Limits of Arbitrariness, in Sign and Sound", 1978; (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - "Analysis, Synthesis and Improvisation", Sweden Symposium, 1980; (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - "Subordinate Future Clauses", 1980 (Box 8)
    - "Kyriolexi and Language Change", 1981; 1983 (Box 9)
    - "Sharp Eyes," ca., 1984; (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - "Distinctions and Generalizations", 1985 (Box 9)
    - "The Group Genitive and Type 24 Languages", 1988 (Box 9)
    - "Stills from Childhood", 1993 (Box 9)
    - Alani's reader Preface, undated (Box 9)
    - Ancient and Modern Style, undated (Box 9)
    - Aristophanes Scholia, undated (Box 9)
    - Draft of Introduction, undated (Box 9)
    - Greek Romance Bibliography, undated (Box 9)
    - "How Different Are They?" Phonology Conference, undated (Box 9)
    - Iowa paper and Illinois, undated (Box 9)
    - "Semantic/Lexical Change", undated (Box 9)
    - Publications, miscellaneous, undated (Box 9)
  - Reviews, 1954-1987 (Box 9)
    - "Philosophy of Proclus", 1951 (Box 9)
    - "Historische Lautlehre des Lateinischen," by Max Niedermann, 1954 (Box 9)
    - "Subjunctive and Opative," by E. Adelaide Hahn, 1954 (Box 9)
    - "The Category of Person in Language" by Paul Forchheimer, 1955 (Box 9)
    - "Économie des changements phonétiques," by André Martine, 1957 (Box 9)
    - Mycenaean Greek Review, I and II, 1957-1959 (Box 9)
    - A Study of Thinking Roger W. Brown's Appendix, 1957 (Box 9)
    - "Studies Presented to Joshua Whatmough on his Sixtieth Birthday," ed. Pulgram, 1958 (Box 9)
    - "A Course in Modern Linguistics", 1959 (Box 9)
    - "Acoustic Theory of Speech Production: with Calculations Based on E-Ray Studies of Russian Articulations" by Gunner Fant, 1961 (Box 9)
    - "Introduction to the Spectrography of Speech," by Ernest Pulgram, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Il Romanzo Classsico by Quinto Catandella, 1962 (Box 9)
    - "The Grammar of English Nominalization," by Robert B. Lees, 1962 (Box 9)
    - "Language Change and Linguists Reconstruction", 1962 (Box 9)
    - "Lucian, Satirical Sketches," by Paul Turner, 1962 (Box 9)
    - "Historical Linguistics: An Introduction," by W.P. Lehmann, 1963 (Box 9)
    - "Trends in European and American Linguistics" ed. Mohrmann, Sommerfelt, Whatmough, 1930-1960; 1963 (Box 9)
    - "Diachronic and Synchronic Aspects of Language," by Alf Sommerfelt, 1964 (Box 9)
    - "Time and Style," by H. Thornton and A. Thornton, 1964 (Box 9)
    - "Validity of Glottochronology", 1964 (Box 9)